So, we're going to go right into where
we were yesterday.
Uh
And we just talked about teptol,
which a human computer found in the
dictionary.
And it means uh
to get used to not Yeah, hardened. To
get used to not using ideas, not using
emptiness.
So, you study it and you you get used to
not using it. So, every time you don't
use it,
uh you get you reinforce your habit not
to use it, right? So, uh
the best place to use it is when someone
irritates you, okay? So, we all have
We will all have many chances every week
to
to think about emptiness, okay?
And it's good to tie those two together
and that's kind of the point of this
class this weekend
is to tie together
emptiness to people who irritate you and
situations that are difficult for you,
okay?
So, that's the whole point of this
class. If you don't If you just come
and you study all the schools of
emptiness and you don't use it
during the break when someone pushes in
front of you and takes the refreshments
before you, then
you kind of flunked the class.
Okay?
Good? All right.
Uh
All right. So, we're on verse 134.
You don't have to follow in the verse.
I I propose that you do it at home.
Uh and I'm going through the
my notes, so I I really suggest your
strategy
uh after today
Well, there's two strategies. One is to
leave the paper in your back seat in
your car
in case uh
someone makes you keep their dog
like happened to me this morning.
Right now.
Uh don't have something to lay on.
Uh the second strategy is to uh uh
take it home with you, okay? And uh
study the
verses with the outline, okay?
All right.
It's not that bad, Kiri.
Uh all right.
No. Okay. Now we're at verse 134. And uh
he's getting deeper
into
uh
people who are doing sophisticated
meditation on one and many. So again, to
just repeat that, cuz it's a little
confusing. Uh it doesn't have much to do
with many, okay?
So you can just cancel the the many. I
like to say one or
more than one is a nice way to say it.
So if
if if something's not coming from its
own side,
if one thing can't come from its own
side, then two things can't come from
its own side. So that's not such a big
deal. So kick out the two things.
Then one thing, how to how to talk about
one thing, when you teach it in New York
in your three jewels,
uh go to the parts of things, you know,
go directly to the parts of things. And
there's something fishy, as Nagarjuna
would say.
You know, there's something fishy, like
it doesn't quite add up. And and you
have
over the course of your life, you tend
to ignore the inconsistencies that you
see. You see what I mean? And you get
used to it, and you live with it, okay?
You you you buy a car,
you know, it's new, it doesn't quite
work right, and you just keep fixing it.
You see, you keep taking it in, you
spend the money, or you sell it. You
you're thinking of these two options.
I can keep taking it back on the
warranty,
and then at some point you lose your
patience and you say, "I'm just going to
sell it, you know, and I'll I'll buy
some other car, and I'll do the best I
can." And those are in your mind, your
only two options, okay? And then the the
option of a person who studied one and
many
is that they would say, "I have to give
more rides to people, okay? If I want my
car to work better, I have to give more
rides to people. And if that's not your
first impulse
when your car starts acting up,
uh you are reinforcing the negative part
of your mind, and that's a big theme
here. Okay? If it's not your first
impulse to give more
when things aren't going well, uh
then you don't have the angel in your
mind. Okay? And it's not some kind of
touchy-feely angel,
you know, like uh
I was asked to give a a talk on
corporate uh what was it? A social
responsibility in corporate corporations
in Japan
and uh
2 weeks ago. And I And it was like I was
just like
there's one thing about social
responsibility in corporations.
Uh you got to understand it drives your
profits. It's nothing nice.
It happens to be nice, that's lucky.
Uh but even if it wasn't nice, you still
have to do it
uh if you want to make money. Okay? The
purpose of a corporation
is that people invest in the
corporation, and those people have
invested say their retirement money,
and they're trying to make money for
their retirement, and it's a good thing.
Corporations are
kind of cool because they're kind of
like everyone's saying I'm going to
support each other.
And we all put money into it, and we all
wait and try to get money out of it. So,
the purpose of a corporation, purpose of
a stock market,
the purpose of modern economic system in
the world
is to supply return to people who
invested in it. And uh that's a nice
thing cuz, you know, young people start
yoga studios and stuff like that
foolishly.
And uh no, I'm just kidding. Or farms.
And uh then they're hoping people will
uh
support them and invest in them, and
those people are hoping they'll get
something back later. So,
so that's a good thing. But But what's
not current thinking
is that if you want those companies to
make money, you have to work more on
helping other people and and supporting
other people, okay?
So, anyway, we talking about that. If
your first
instinct when you're trying to start a
yoga studio or or a farm or whatever is
not to
help other people with yoga studios and
farms especially,
then uh
you don't have an angel in your mind and
you will fail or you won't do as well as
you could have, okay? If you If you
succeed, it's all the angels in your
mind, okay?
All right.
So,
now we're talking about uh I promised
you yesterday what? Do you remember at
the very last thing I said? Hmm, I'm not
going to bet any money cuz it's
you should remember. What was the very
last thing I said? I promised you today.
This This thing gets to say something.
Yeah.
They're going to do versus
Yeah, the devil proposes he he covers
the meditation, which helps a little
bit, okay? All the ones up to now didn't
help at all. Now, supposedly we're going
to get one that helps a little bit.
What's weird about this section, if you
live with it, if you sit with it for a
while,
is who's giving advice about correct
emptiness meditation.
It's the devil
and it's all in a negative context. He's
saying uh
you know, if you really wanted to kick
me out, you would do this and this and
this, but you're not, so, you know,
don't blame me.
Okay? But, it's it's kind of ironic uh
he goes Now, he's going to go into
some correct emptiness meditations and
he's going to say, "If you had done
that, I would be worried, but you're
not."
Okay? So, it's kind of ironic that the
devil
uh is giving the advice here. Uh
and I I like it. I like the idea of uh
your ignorance is not uh
misinformed.
Okay?
Okay? Like he's not completely stupid.
Your ignorance is clever. It's been
there for a long, long time and he's
been preserving himself. He's been
taking care of himself. Okay? The the
devil in the world is not stupid.
You know, obviously crude, arrogant,
immoral people
uh are not the devil. It's the people
who It's your friends who are
sophisticated and cool and nice and
you know, waste your time. Okay?
All right. Uh
so,
this number 134
is you stay on the fact that me myself
is not self-existent.
And you're still trying to understand
the thought process, right? So, we said
DCI level seven, for example, which is
all devoted to what?
The parrot causes What'd you say?
Causes to see emptiness.
What's the name of
DCI level seven?
Touching the diamond world. We don't use
the word emptiness. We don't say direct
perception. Okay?
Try to learn the
lingo.
Okay? That protects you when you go
different places. Okay?
So, trying to trying to reach that
Yeah, there's approximate causes what
they call proximate causes in logic,
which is like study
uh you know,
read books, meditate a lot.
Things like that. But, the real cause is
sharing what you know, right? Sharing as
much as you know.
So,
now at this point the devil is examining
the thought process, which kind of
understands one and many. Okay? By now,
after two days of all this,
you know, you're either fed up with it
and you're anxious to go home.
Or you're like, I kind of get it now.
You know, I kind of get it. Recasts
parts.
Uh but, you can't really
you can't be seeing what you see. It
cannot be coming from Rick. You cannot
be seeing the left arm and the right arm
at the same time.
And and even if your eye catches the
left arm, there's a problem that you
have to see the left part of the left
arm and the right part of the left arm.
And it just endless. And
what you're seeing cannot be coming from
the borders that divide uh, his you
know, like the cow in the butcher shop
they have
uh,
lines of the parts and uh,
and it's like that, you know, you want
to think it's like that, but it's not.
There's no borders between his pieces.
What you see is impossible, okay? So,
you got that. You're there already,
okay?
Now, he wants you to explore how did you
get there? You see, what kind of things
did you do to get in this room? You
know, you are one person out of
I don't know. You are one person out of
2 million
You're one person out of I don't know, 5
million people in the United States.
10 million people, okay? You are one
person out of 10 million people in the
United States who got here today, okay?
So, we got to explore
how did your mind get here? You know,
how does your mind understanding this
stuff right now? And then he says
meditate on it. Meditate on your mind.
See how it's understanding these things
today. But understand
what?
Yeah, that the mind is Well, that and
Yeah, I'm good. But you're also uh,
even when you're thinking right about
your So, he says, if you come to a good
understanding of your own thought
process, right?
If you focus on your own mind at this
moment
and you say I got here by by sharing
what I understand in my life, by trying
to make other people's lives better.
That's how my mind is understanding
today's class, okay?
Does Is that
emptiness?
Is it useful?
Yeah, it'll take you to emptiness, okay?
Got it? So, the devil's like, "Look,
that doesn't contradict me."
Okay, it's not like dark and light in
the same room, right?
That's what we want to get to. Seeing
poof
and the devil's continued existence
inside your head
uh
they can't exist in the same place at
the same time. But, a mild examination
of the causes,
even the karmic causes of why you're
understanding me right now,
is not exactly light that's going to
banish the darkness. It's just kind of
like a flashlight.
But, if you're not understanding that
that is emptiness as
well.
Yeah, right.
just reinforcing your Yeah, and yeah,
that's true, too. That's true, too. So,
what he's talking about here, where he
got here was uh you're getting closer
because the thing you're examining is
close to Mike.
Okay? And when you see emptiness
directly for the first time, it will be
the emptiness of Rig or the emptiness of
Bonnie or the emptiness of Lucia or the
emptiness of Bertha. You see your own
emptiness first, okay?
So, he's a little nervous
because you're getting close to
you, okay? You're getting close to Mike
or Anatole, okay? And and that's
dangerous for him cuz that's the that's
the emptiness
you see first when you see emptiness
directly. When I did my Geshe,
there's a film, right? There's a video
of the last few minutes and the what the
question the guy asking me
and he came down from uh North India to
debate me, to kick to kick this guy's
butt. And uh I remember and it was kind
of cool. and he was one of the last
questioners and that was his question.
We went off on that. Which which
emptiness do you see
direct Which emptiness do you see when
you see emptiness directly is me. But
when you're studying it, you start with
things. Yeah, things in your world.
Okay?
All right. So, he says verse 134, "I'm
nervous because you're getting close to
the emptiness of
you." And that kind of connects to a
Buddhist idea about who is you.
Which is what? Do you guys remember?
You know, hmm.
There's some schools that don't that say
that Nick
is not a changing thing which is neither
mental or physical. There's some schools
that say that Nick is
That would be a concept, yeah.
It it's a changing thing, but it's
It's the witness mind.
Uh some schools say that that's that's
word or that's Earl is the person who
listens to the thoughts in your head.
Some schools, very high schools
high schools uh will say that this is uh
this is Earl, okay? The the the part of
the the awareness of your thought.
Yugan amba shipa is uh is you, okay?
So, right now we're investigating the
emptiness of the consciousness of your
thought and it's close to The devil's
getting worried cuz you're close to to
you.
Okay, what?
Yeah, right. Yeah. Yeah. Well, thoughts
include all your sense perceptions of
the previous moment, technically.
Okay?
All right.
Nick, did you have a question?
No, I I they still count it as a heap.
Yeah. And And you could kick out the
physical senses.
Awareness of the physical senses anyway.
Okay.
All right. Uh then uh verse 135, the
devil says,
"Look, uh you inflict only minor damage,
but that's the first time we have
inflicted minor damage. So, it's kind of
encouraging. All right?"
Uh
then he goes off on that a little bit
and he says uh
"So, suppose you do start thinking about
uh
your parts, but even when you do think
about Rick's arms and legs and head,
uh you still
aren't aware of the final part. Okay,
what do I mean when I say final part?"
Yeah, yeah. So, you know, as I often
say, I
I get really frustrated listening to uh
Buddhist teachers, frankly.
And uh they'll say, "Oh, you're not you,
and you're not Your parts are not you."
And then I'm waiting.
And then
they say, "All your parts are not you."
And I say, "Well, if all your parts are
not you, then what else is you?" You see
what I mean?
What's the punchline?
The final part is
Yeah, one of the parts is the luminous
image that comes out of the karmic seed.
Okay, so karmic seed opens in your mind.
A picture comes out that's about this
big.
It covers Mike.
And then
then the legs and arms and body, the
mind,
all together become Mike, but they need
that last part. Without that last part,
they are not Mike. Okay? Then you can
say
the parts are not the whole, but they
mean the parts minus the
karmic image, yeah, is not Mike. Okay?
You got that. All right.
That's verse 136.
Then he says, uh this tent this tendency
to feel
that the parts of Rick are Rick is
insidious.
It means nasty.
Uh cuz it follows you all the way up to
the 10th Bodhisattva level. He claims in
verse 137
that the habit
of thinking that Rick is all the all the
things I can see of Rick coming at me
that habit continues even in a high
Bodhisattva, even past the seventh
Bodhisattva level. He's talking about
the subtle stain
of that habit, okay?
You're still thinking about it. Here's
the
No, it no longer appears that way after
the eighth level. Uh after the seventh
level. So, it's called Nyingen
Nyingen lemba for $100.
I'll take it that way.
Except Break it down.
Definitely it's the same as long as
Well, Nyingen Nyingen lem.
You don't Come on, you're just
floundering. You don't you don't take
this stuff existing.
Kind of prana. Wait, I want an
explanation of the technical word for
that point, which is called Nyingen
lemba.
It just
be taken out. Nyingen Nyingen
Nyingen. Okay, Nyingen is place, uh
situation. Ngen means bad.
Uh like Ding-ngen means when you can't
give an answer to your teacher in the
monastery, they say Ding-ngen, which
means uh
evil omen or something.
Uh so, it means that Nyingen lemba is uh
Our hearts do Nyingen lemba, but they
don't do bad karma.
Okay? Our hearts do Nyingen example is
jumping inelegantly.
Go figure. Chom chom.
Chom
Ja chom chom.
Uh okay, meaning uh you still do
like what do you call that? Rowdy
things, but they're not bad karma, okay?
How's that? And uh they still reflect
some kind of uh
stain uh some kind of shadow. It's a
shadow of an old karmic seed, okay? But
it's not the karmic seed anymore, okay?
It's called shadow of an old karmic
seed. How's that?
And that follows a bodhisattva to the
10th level, okay? Until they become a
a Buddha, okay? Cuz it's a
shady.
Right? Obstacle to omniscient, okay? Got
it?
Okay, and that's 137. So you got Nying
and Lambar, and if you don't get it
again, you owe me $100, okay? Hey, human
computer.
We went over that at least once or
twice, okay?
The cool thing about the translation
classes upstairs is that we are covering
all of Buddhism
every
you know, three times a year
for 2 weeks, and it's I taught 72
classes in January.
And they are hard. They take many hours
of preparation, and uh
you can get bathed in Buddhism. You can
get all the great ideas of Buddhism.
Just listen to it on YouTube, right?
It's on YouTube.
Yeah, don't you know, just listen to it
from Listen to it in your car or
something. Don't don't pay attention.
Just expose your head to it, okay? And I
tell you we've been doing it for a
couple years now, and uh
it's amazing what the effect it has on
your mind and your life, okay? Like
it's amazing what it does to
just to be bathed in all the schools of
Buddhism once every 4 months or so,
okay?
So and it's free, and just do it, okay?
People complain to me, "Wah wah wah."
This is not free. I say, "Yeah." Okay,
there's How many
$200 of free deep classes last year. So
just You're you're crazy if you don't
listen to them. I don't know.
Okay.
And and that's all of Buddhism except
for secret Buddhism. We're not covering
secret Buddhism
in in the open.
So yeah, I said just text counts, okay?
138. Uh
Now, he starts to talk about this is
easy, Nick. So, I'm going to give it to
you cuz you're, you know, you look kind
of fresh today. I don't know what
happened. Uh
You don't work on Sundays, right?
Just kidding.
Oh, that's why you're pumped up. Okay.
What's the difference between nyamshak,
yeshe, and jetop yeshe? One is the
meditation during the direct or you're
having the direct perception of
emptiness. The other one is the
subsequent wisdom where you realize the
16 aspects of the four applications.
Yeah, nice. Did you ever hear that?
Yeah. So, there's a division of the
experience of emptiness
into the direct experience, which is
like 20 minutes
of direct experience of higher reality.
And then there's what they call the
aftermath.
Uh
math means the cutting of the harvest or
something. It's a nice word. It means
enjoying the smell of the hay
afterwards.
And I like it. And it's uh
And so, you can divide a person's a high
a high being's experience of emptiness
can be divided into two parts. One is
the direct perception. And then the
second is this kind of fragrance.
Enjoying the fragrance afterwards called
aftermath, okay? Verse number 138
talks about the aftermath. And it says,
"Bodhisattvas", although it should have
said "Aryas".
Uh
even during the aftermath, they are
utpala.
Something wrong.
They still see things as They still see
things as coming from their own side,
okay? So, uh this habit or this tendency
to see Rick as coming from from Rick's
side
and not from me, okay? Uh it stays with
you even after you see emptiness
directly. It It reasserts itself even in
an Arya, okay? So, therefore, Aryas
don't rid themselves of the
what form of inborn inborn form of a
misunderstanding the world. They cannot
They do not, by the act of being an
Arya,
uh rid themselves of that tendency.
Someone told me,
a very high source, wrong, uh
said an Arya should be able to fly
and read, you know, all this stuff. And
it's not true at all. No No text says
that in in the Buddhism.
Uh
You'll only lose three things at that
time, which is what? Give me one.
Doubt about the path.
Yeah, intellectual belief that what
you're seeing is correct. And then
Yeah, doing stupid things like hurting
your body cuz you, you know, like
whipping yourself or, uh uh
refusing to eat ice cream.
Uh
Doing yoga.
Yeah, I'd put that in there.
When I was betting people, on one day I
bet somebody 20 bucks they couldn't lose
my yoga mat.
Okay.
Uh
Okay, so one verse 138 is talking about
this fact that a person who's just seen
emptiness doesn't uh rid themselves.
They don't clean out this habit of
seeing things as coming from their own
side, but they don't believe it anymore.
I like the image of I always give the
image of uh what's his name? You
Ulysses?
Uh is going past the land of the sirens
on his boat, on his way to get the
golden fleece. Odysseus
Oh, Odysseus? I don't know. It's this
Greek dude.
Yeah, and alien. And he really wants to
listen to the song of the sirens. And
the sirens sing
on the rocky shore, and then the sailors
get enchanted and want to meet them, and
they crash their ships, and the ladies
take all their stuff.
Which is just like real life.
Uh and then just kidding.
I know. I know. I know.
We can say it both ways.
Uh
But uh he says, "Tie me to the mast, and
uh
because I want to hear the song, and
then don't believe anything I say.
You know, don't listen to anything.
Don't listen to your captain when he
tells you to turn the boat, okay? So,
for he probably put a time limit on it,
right?
Like for the next hour, don't listen to
anything I say.
And that's kind of what an arya feels
like, you know? Cuz this this call, the
siren call of thinking that things come
from their own side,
but the aryas like, "I'm crazy. I'm
crazy, you know?"
The king who was informed by his
minister that the water supplies of the
kingdom were poisoned,
and that anyone who drank the water
would go crazy.
And the king said, "Well, just get me a
private water supply." And this minister
said, "We can't. That it's going to
affect all the water in the kingdom."
So, the king said, "Put a big X on my
head.
You know, get a
magic marker,
and put a big X on my head, and whenever
I see myself in the mirror, I'll
remember I'm crazy from the water."
And then he They did it, and he put the
X on his head, and he drank the water,
and then he was always wondering what
the X on his head was for when he looked
in the mirror. Okay.
Uh that's how an arya feels. Okay.
Verse um
Now, he goes on in that verse 138 to to
say how other people experience the
aftermath, okay? So, how does a Buddha
experience the aftermath?
Do they still see things coming this
way? No, okay? So, for
it's not legal, he's points out, to talk
about nyam shak and jetob direct and
aftermath for a Buddha. You can't say it
doesn't apply
to a a Buddha and a
to a Buddha, okay? Then he says, "Normal
people have no
That's so forget non-Arya.
Yeah, they don't have either one, okay?
They don't have the direct experience
and they don't have the aftermath. So he
gives three moves.
Okay, he gives three permutations. Okay,
there's people who have neither. There's
people who have both.
And there's people who are Okay, you got
it. All right.
Verse 139.
Uh we have a tendency if
And this is a famous teaching on
emptiness that you tend to think of
things as more self-existent when you're
upset.
Halt, right? H A L
H A A L T
and hungry, angry
anxious
lonely and tired, okay? And he's going
to talk more about that, uh which is
interesting cuz this is a big NVC thing.
This is a big nonviolent communication
thing. You know, when you're hungry,
when you're angry, when you're upset
when you're lonely, when you're tired,
you tend to be more vulnerable
to attacks of bad communication, which
means yelling at people.
And uh
so
he says, uh people are more likely
You're more likely to have trouble
uh around someone that you're having a
problem with. Your your emptiness
understanding is going to dip
when you get in contact with people who
irritate you, okay?
Verse 140.
Uh
you can get on
you can think about the flow
of the understanding of emptiness and
you can break it down into parts
temporally, in time.
Okay? And you guys know this example.
What's example for $50 in the
Bodhisattva Chariot of Tara?
Um mala.
Oh, damn.
Peter, 50.
Okay, yeah, a rosary
is the example in the Bodhisattva
Chariot of Tara for emptiness over time,
parts over time.
And what's the example for for $0
Uh of uh statically? Army. Yeah, an army
or a force. Okay, yeah. Okay.
All right. Mm,
so
only one verse 140 says, "Only small
damage to me
if you treat
the moments of your understanding of
emptiness today during this class as
parts
and start to understand that those parts
are being glued together
by the act of sharing what you
understand with others in the past.
Okay? Small damage to me. So, we're
getting into the field of small damage.
Not bad.
Not bad. Um
Then he says in 141,
okay?
"If you don't understand the luminous
image thing, I will dance on top of your
head."
And he uses these words, okay?
I kind of like it. What are those words?
Let me check. Um
the word will be interesting.
Yeah, nanyi phumbu tengdu gyin. Okay,
nanyi phumbu tengdu gyin. Nanyi means I
will me and nobody else, meaning no
wisdom.
Phumbu on top of your body and mind. Uh
tengdu on top of it. Gyin means Do you
know gyin?
Gyin means uh
I saw a video of Mick Jagger. Uh
You know.
Yeah, it means strut.
Gyin means uh strut. Uh
We're thinking to do uh
Give Me Shelter in Taiwan with a bunch
of
the organizers singing. So, it's kind of
dangerous.
Uh
but uh anyway, okay, JB?
You're the one who's has to keep
together.
He will ging on on top of your uh
ignorance will ging on top of your uh
body and mind, okay? Huh?
Oh, good question. Uh
aum ga
ya ta ngi gya. Aum ga ya ta ngi gya ki
ngi ngi ngi ngi ngi ngi ngi okay? If you
want to know the spelling, okay?
In In Tibetan you when you say c a t
cat, you have to say c
c a ka c a t cat.
Anyway, this is the rule.
But, it's dying out even as we speak.
Okay, 142.
Then he says uh
so I'm not your body and I'm not your
mind and if you think I am, I'm going to
dance on top of your body and mind.
But, by the way, don't think I'm
something divorced
from your body and mind. And this gets
into which we're going to do the eternal
schools of
Hinduism which say that like the Jains
for $0
the self is
Come on. Big umbrella. It looks like a
big mushroom
and it's uh you know, I don't know. Self
liberation.
Oh, sorry. Okay, anyway.
Uh
it's like a big mushroom that hangs on
your head and it's kind of a halo thing,
okay? So, he says
in verse 142 uh
to believe that there is a part of
Michael which is not here, which is
somehow uh
a soul. To believe that is also a
mistake, okay? A soul that doesn't come
from you.
Okay, Michael can have a soul
if you talk about wisdom as a soul or
something like that. But if it if it
doesn't come from how you treat other
people, it doesn't exist, even the soul.
Okay? So, there is no soul who suffers
or gets
pleasure from the things that you do.
Okay? The soul is the pleasure or
suffering you get from the things you
do. Okay? And maybe God is the law of
karma.
You could say it that way. Okay? And and
that would be
acceptable. Okay? And that might be in a
good way to teach it to people who are
attracted to that idea. Okay?
All right.
1:43
Uh
and I'll just only when you see that
Michael cannot exist without the
luminous image coming out of your karmic
seeds
uh are you doing damage to me? Okay?
When When you see he cannot exist
without the picture. Okay? When you see
the
nothing that's happening to you in your
life could be happening without karmic
seeds
then you then you then you're getting
there. Okay? Then you're damaging
that habit. So, again, that goes back to
two husbands in the kitchen.
Which uh you you know, if you teach it,
there's a fun way to teach it.
And I I don't have time to do it today,
but uh you know, get in touch with
Anatole.
Anatole has an interesting job. He gets
paid
to uh look at all my videos over and
over.
Uh
hundreds and hundreds, 5,000.
And he cuts out the concepts and and we
use them in our teacher training. So,
every time Geshe La taught the two
husbands
uh
he he he heard it like three, four, five
times.
And he cuts it out and he and he sends
it in he puts it online for our teacher
training. And uh
I would wager that the early ones are
not similar to the later ones. You see,
it continues to evolve.
But what's fun in the two husbands
thing, you know, look at some of the
recent videos.
Yeah, I mean
Uh and uh
just see
just see uh
there's something very cool that during
that skit you can identify just about
every major Buddhist concept. You see,
uh you can
you know, and it's fun when you're
teaching it to an audience
who's Buddhist to say, "Where do you
think's the dependent origination?" Uh
where's the gacha?
Where's the two gachas, you know? Uh
where's where's nirvana?
When at what moment did the lady have a
nirvana-ish experience, you see? And and
like that, okay? Where's the
self-existence?
And and it's really nice to do it that
way. Uh you can you can really get
everything in there if you're if you're
careful. So you can look at the more
recent videos.
Uh
Okay, 144.
Uh you have to reach the feeling of
poof, okay? 144 verse 144 is poof verse.
Okay, and it's like you got to get to
this poof experience. Who wants to take
a shot at a poof experience that's not
with the
with the email and the husband.
Yeah, I mean it's too depressing. You
got another one for me? Something you
really expected to be there and then
poof.
You got a good one for me?
Anybody.
Peter filter. Go to Sedona and you
expect to be really hot and then the
plane opens noise for you.
Okay.
Yeah, the image of hot Sedona
uh goes poof. Yeah, okay.
A good give me one with the
hippopotamus.
I mean not in that case.
Not in that particular case.
If it's this is poof. You got what? Wait
a minute.
Wait, I want to proof something over
here. Give me a proof.
Any proof.
And you can't use Discover card. I
already used that.
Wait, be be uh say louder.
I used my Discover card. Oh, Discover
card is pretty good, yeah. Yeah, Jim
Tone brought me uh
a menu from New York, and on the back it
said, "We do not accept credit and
Discover credit card."
Anybody else? You got proof? You just
wanted drive your car and you expect
that your key
is going to make the car run. Good. And
and you reach into your purse and you
realize you brought the wrong one. And
there's no key in there.
And then the thing is the key was not
the thing that started the car in the
first place.
Anyway.
Okay, and that's not Ben. Okay.
proof than that. Come on, proof me.
So, Ben
I'll ding if you proof.
This is a real story.
Ben Kramer, I have to pick something up
at a house I was staying at. One of the
terms Yeah. uh I was like, "Kramer, can
you drive me?" He's like He's like, "Ah,
I don't feel like it. Can you just take
yourself?" I was like, "Okay." So, he
gives me the keys to his car. So, I'm
like, "Okay, I'll just drive." And so
then I go, I get in the car, and you
know, it's a Prius, so you're supposed
to be in the car with the key and go,
right? So, when nothing's happening,
nothing's working, I'm like, "What is
going on?" I was like I was like, "Is
this What did Kramer give me?" And I was
like, "Ah, Ben. Damn you." And then And
then I realized I was in the wrong car.
No.
I was in Ben of Phil's Prius.
That's a good one.
That's proof. All right, I got to ding.
Me and V were in San Diego. We went to a
pizza parlor, and she got
She got She came out and sat in the
wrong car, but the the owner was sitting
right in front of me. Yeah.
He was kind of
I was kind of
wasn't good.
Okay, 1:45.
Uh
1:45 the devil describes a perfect
emptiness meditation. And if you look at
my notes, I just note how weird it is
that after 144 verses
the
the person telling us what real
emptiness meditation
is is the devil, you know? So,
he just says
uh you'll see that there's no me
uh without a luminous image, there's no
me, okay? Without without us image
coming out of your karmic seed, there's
no me, okay?
And uh but then he adds something cool,
which he says
uh
and especially you're going to have to
maintain the high quality of the
meditation.
The meditation's going to have to be
high quality, okay? Got it? So, he's
This is the first time
someone has mentioned shamatha
uh with vipassana. Uh vipashyana, sorry.
Uh vipashyana, okay? This is the first
time uh anyone, I think, has said "By
the way, you're going to need this
platform
of a deep of a good meditative
ability if you want to really sustain
this state of mind." And then they're
going to kind of get into sustaining the
state of mind, okay? So, in the class
with Geshe Michael there,
you control yourself, the person next to
you irritates you big time.
And you're like struggling with it, and
you're like, "Oh, they're empty, they're
empty, and it's just a luminous image."
And then
then you get outside of this building
and you just lose it, okay? Somehow
being out This is kind of like holy
ground, right, Seiji? This is becoming
holy ground.
You can feel the change in the building,
I think. Will wasn't here for a while
and just feel the change
in the What do you call patina?
Dharma patina of the building is
increasing and it's kind of cool. Three
Jewels is doing that. The new Three
Jewels is doing that, too.
Uh so, anyway, uh
yeah, he's going to start talking about
sustaining
uh the experience, okay? All right,
1:46.
Uh
if you were able to
think these thoughts and sustain a
regular meditation practice, okay?
Then he says, "That would hurt me."
That's the kind of he says, "That would
hurt me." But, 1:46, let me I want to
get the Tibetan. Uh
Come on, I know you can do it.
I'll just do it manually. Oh, I see,
it's not in this reading. Hey, we
finished the first reading.
Okay.
Uh now I got it. I got it. It's okay. I
can't read it anyway. I'm going to go
off this.
Uh
Okay, good. Uh
Dingtang Kyong la Khen na ni, if you get
good at maintaining
this view and the meditation below it,
you are contradicting the way I see
things.
Uh then you could boopa me. Boopa?
It's not very common. Yeah, you could
expel me
from the mind. Yeah, it's not poof, it's
boop. Uh no, it's different.
You're spelling something which
certainly does exist,
which is misunderstanding.
Uh
Nice. Nice. Very nice. I'm glad I didn't
bet.
Uh nyin mo means in the daytime. Karma
means uh Karma in Tibetan means star.
Okay? And I think he's trying to allude
to another star for
$3.
Huh?
Yeah, the back end of the Diamond Cutter
Sutra. Okay, I only three bucks.
Karma lovely mommy don't give me
something what you be doing me love and
all that kind of thing
you know. What's the Sanskrit?
Taraka. Taraka. Yeah, Taraka means star.
Okay.
So, I think he's trying to allude
you know, this is star during the day,
star in broad daylight nimmo. Okay, star
in broad daylight is
a Buddhist expression for an
impossibility.
But it's also recall I think he's
purposely recalling the last verse of
the Diamond Cutter Sutra and anyone want
to
give me two interpretations of that? We
We did a whole
We did it for like a week. We did that
verse for like a week. We did like five
commentaries on it.
I'm just the star? Shoot. Get Do the
easy one. Let somebody else do the hard
one.
Okay, one of them is that
our
our karma ripening is like stars on a
black sky. Okay.
The sky is emptiness, the night sky.
Good. That's the one I didn't remember,
so that's even better.
Anybody else?
Yeah.
There was There was one about stars
being reflected in the bucket of water.
Yeah.
And so kind of unreal. Yeah. There was
one like that. There's two more I can
think of.
Anybody?
Uh
wisdom in the human mind is like
starlight in the dark, you know, like
it's a What do you call a ray of hope?
And then there was one more. One more
obvious one.
Don't forget there's two themes to the
final verse of the
Yeah, impermanence. That when the sun
comes up this the stars fade every day.
Okay.
All right, cool.
Now, but he's comparing the person who
has a strong meditative platform and
who's understanding emptiness at the
same time and who's able to maintain it
or what do you call it?
Sustain it outside of the building.
Outside of the class, okay? Even during
the refreshment break.
When is the refreshment break?
Maybe another 10 minutes or so. How's
that?
Okay, we have refreshments.
Yeah.
All right, it's really bad you know,
when we do DCI teacher training we say,
"Make sure there's refreshments before
you announce them."
Okay, that's like number one teacher
training thing.
All right, so uh
yeah.
A person who understands
emptiness clearly
and who can call it up that
understanding when they're tired or
hungry or angry
uh is as common as a star shining at
noon. Okay.
This is who? Who says that?
Yeah, unfortunately he's correct.
Okay, and it's the same for us, you
know, like I had a challenge this
morning and I was like, "Come on, you're
going to teach it in an hour, maybe you
could use it."
And I'm like, "No, I don't want to."
Okay. Uh
It wasn't anybody here, don't worry.
and I'm going to read you this
Uh you live with me every moment, but
you don't see me.
People who say they're going to kick me
out.
Okay, uh look, so there's two words here
that you guys don't know, okay? One is
de.
De. Say de.
And one is Lu, okay? And day means uh
donde, which means uh a spirit being, a
negative spirit, uh evil spirit, okay?
Who's who's harassing you? They're
called harassing spirits.
Donde, or demo for $10?
Female spirit being.
20?
30? 40? 50?
Forget it, cancel.
Demo means uh yeti,
uh abominable snowman.
Okay? But so they may be related, I
think. But the day just day by itself
means uh
a spirit that hassles you. And there's a
custom to make a Lu, okay? So Lu, easy
way to make a Lu is to uh
get a uh
Yeah, I don't know.
Go to a restaurant that serves soft
rolls.
And then uh squeeze it into a
this shape, and then uh push this side
and push this side, and then drop it on
the ground discreetly when the waitress
isn't looking.
And that's called a Lu, okay? And then
that's supposed to
draw
it's supposed to distract the spirit
from harassing you. Then you get in your
car and you drive away, and they're
still trying to eat this Lu, you know?
So
but the uh there's a joke, okay? This is
Tibetan humor, which is really
dry
uh
and not very funny, actually. But um but
they laugh.
Uh so it must be cultural. Um
if you dropped a Lu in the back door,
but the demon's in the front door,
that that's what this verse is about. So
I was trying to think of a common
example, like you your wife gets mad at
you,
you buy her a bouquet of flowers,
and you put it
in a vase,
and you
drive home, and you put it in front of
the neighbor's front door.
You see, and your wife never sees it.
That's the idea, okay? So, he's talking
about uh
people who say they're going to
kick me out of their mind
are people leaving vases of flowers for
their wife at the neighbor's door
because they don't even see me, and I'm
there all day. You see what I mean? Got
it? So, I'm there all day,
and they're like studying Buddhism so
they can identify me.
You know?
And I'm just there while they're
studying Buddhism, also, and they don't
see me, you know? It's like
when I taught this at uh what do you
call that place? Sivananda.
I handed out uh
those paper sunglasses,
and people forget they have the
sunglasses on after a while. You see
what I mean? It's hard to see the
sunglasses
when you've been wearing them for more
than an hour or so.
Um
So, you've had this glasses,
rose-colored glasses,
poop-colored glasses, your whole life,
and you don't see that you have a mind.
And then you're you're studying Buddhism
to try to identify the demon, and he's
on your top of your head ginging while
you're studying. You see what I mean?
So, uh he's talking about that.
Uh and then he starts uh with a couple
of nice images about similar
thoughts, okay? So, verse number 148
is uh shooting an arrow at a target with
a blindfold on, okay? So, you say you're
going to go after ignorance.
Ignorance is in your mind while you're
going after ignorance, and then you
study study study to find the ignorance,
and the ignorance the ignorance is
singing in your mind the whole time
you're studying,
and you don't notice. You don't You
don't know. Okay, got it? It's part and
parcel of your experience, so it's hard
to identify. You know what's really hard
to identify also is awareness.
You know, so we have these classes
upstairs. We we talk for hours after
hour.
And then we we used to translate
numbership of vijnana as consciousness,
but I think awareness is closer. And um
it's hard to identify that you're aware.
You see? No rare rarely do you do it.
Cuz you never lose it. And you know,
even in deep states of meditation,
you still have awareness. You see? So,
something that's going on all the time,
you don't notice. You know, it's like
your partner,
you know, or something. You get used to
them.
They have a rule at the monastery.
They have all They have a special room
with uh
football lockers.
Hundreds of lockers. And
because people donate paintings to the
monastery. So, as you know,
at Diamond Mountain. And so, you have
hundreds of paintings, thousands.
And there's a rule that you have to
rotate them every 6 weeks or something.
There's a rule in the monastery. The the
gonyer,
which is the temple keeper.
He has to
change them every 6 months. Why?
Cuz you stop noticing them. You don't
notice them anymore. And then the gonyer
does his thing, you know. By the way,
they take the worst 10 monks. He gets
those guys.
Cuz they have to stand there with sticks
and hang thankas all day.
And then you come in and you're like,
"Wow, the thankas are so nice today, you
know?" Okay? Unfortunately, you never
change your ignorance out. It's been
there since you were born and it's
always going to be there. So, verse
number
147 148 40 48 is shooting
at a target
uh with your with a blindfold on. Okay?
Uh 149, he switches to the positive. He
switches to the positive, okay? You are
digging for rubies,
but you don't know what color they are.
Okay, somebody says here here's a shovel
and dig for rubies, you know, and you
dig and dig and dig and then whole after
the whole day you're all sweaty and
you're all dirty and you
you say,
"Did you get any?" And they said, "Well,
no, I didn't know what color they are."
Okay? So, that's
a comment on wisdom, okay? That's a
comment on understanding
uh, where Rick's coming from. And if you
don't know what you're looking for,
you'll never find it, okay?
All right.
Then that devil in that same jewel
verse, he says, "Uh, wisdom, you're
someone no one ever meets.
I am master of the universe."
I I like that.
Okay.
150.
Uh, he goes back to ineffective
meditations. And if you're interested,
if you're keeping count, which I decided
to keep count, he's on number 21, okay?
So, here's
here's
kind of stupid meditation number 21. I
don't want to say stupid in a
in a text translation cuz it's stupid,
okay?
All right.
Number 21.
The problem is is that it's comfortable
to leave me where I am.
You know, it's more comfortable for
people not to
not to face this
these ideas. And it happens to me
because my job upstairs
is to read all the translators'
translations. I have to prepare before
the classes, which means I have to find
all the references before they get to
class.
Many hours of work. Then I have to make
sure I understand what the book's about.
And sometimes it's really really hard,
you know? And and I find myself uh
resisting it.
You know, like I get to a hard idea and
I'm like uh
I don't really have to explain this
deep, you know? I don't have to go this
deep. Maybe I can just let it go. You Do
you do that?
Uh like I just reach a point where uh
no human being would would be asked to
go this deep.
I did it yesterday. I was translating
some proper and it just I was just like,
"Come on."
You know, no one's ever going to know
that I didn't talk about it.
You know? And I'm like,
then there's this moment of honesty, you
know? You're like, "But if you don't
talk about it, who's going to talk about
it?" You know? And you're like,
"All right." You know? It takes another
3 hours to figure it out or something.
You have to look at many, many texts and
and like that. So, what he Ignorance is
saying in 150
is that the human being
uh
takes the easy way out, you know? Water
flows What do you call it? Downhill.
Downhill. You just like, "Why do I have
to
You get to an idea about emptiness and
you take a break cuz it you're it's
uncomfortable.
It's like hitting a rock when you're
digging in your farm.
And you're like, "I'll leave that one
for Annie."
You know? Like you don't say anything.
You just leave it there.
And maybe she'll come across it later,
you know? And uh
that's human nature, okay? So, 150
is about this human nature thing where
we avoid
thinking hard. It's It's It's hard,
especially when you're tiring or
or you know, it's It takes a lot of
discipline
to say, "I'm going to stick with this
another half hour and see if I can
figure it out." Okay? And and what the
devil says
in 150 is that human nature is to let it
go.
And you just go do something else, you
know? Go eat some ice cream or watch
Netflix.
And then maybe you never get back to it.
So, there is a kind of beauty
for us guys, Buddhists, Dharma people,
where you confront ideas and you refuse
to let go. You're like a dog What do you
call it?
A dog who won't let go of a bone. And
And I think you have to be
Part of my job is to be a cheerleader,
right? I'm I'm I'm saying
to you guys, when you get to those
ideas,
uh don't let it go. You know, just stay
with it.
And it's very powerful to come back the
next day, okay? It's a very very
powerful to come back to it the next
day. So, when you're translating,
what I like to do is read the whole
thing first.
When I have When I'm in a good mood,
I used to go for a walk with the
scripture in my hand. So, I'll go for a
long walk down a country road with some
nice trees,
and I'll just read it.
All the the part I want to translate,
I'll read it
until I got a pretty good understanding
of it. Then I stop, I turn around.
Then I walk home, I read it again, okay?
And And then I'm home and I set it down.
Then I translate it the next day, okay?
Uh and I don't start translating till I
understand it perfectly.
Okay? Like almost to the point where I
could recite it. So, try Just a personal
advice,
when you when you're trying to read this
text or similar texts,
uh don't avoid the hard parts. Like
become a
some kind of tough guy who's who It's on
Compass, you know,
famous for just going after the hard
parts. And that's a little excessive.
But when you hit a hard part, then be
persistent and don't Don't be a wimp.
You know, when something's their idea,
especially with these translations, like
try to read them.
and you'll hit stuff and you'll say,
"This is weird. I I don't know."
Then don't go on. Just keep doing it,
reading it over and over and over again,
okay? And the understanding you get from
those moments is very precious.
Then your mind level goes higher, okay?
And your understanding goes deep.
It's really cool, okay? If you If you're
listening to the translation uh
videos and you and you you just
something goes over your head, stop it
and go back and listen to it again, you
know? Stanley's good at that. Stanley's
still writing me
about an idea I refused to finish
in China like 3 weeks ago
in a in a talk. And uh I kind of didn't
want to finish it cuz I didn't
understand it perfectly.
And he keeps writing me, and uh you got
to be like that. He keeps writing me. I
was like, "Let it go, man."
And uh
So, get that habit. If you're going to
be an emptiness person, you got to have
this habit, okay?
All right, take a break. See you in two
What? 2:12, Tim?
2:12?
Okay. 2:15?
There's bathrooms upstairs, okay? If you
need.
Couple things.
Uh first thing,
stop talking.
First thing, uh
April 12th to 21st, Diamond Mountain
Retreat Center. They'll be uh Lamrim,
okay? Lamrim means
steps of the path to enlightenment. You
all know what it's about. I think it's
number 33.
Uh
Yeah.
So, that's about, I don't know, call it
uh
$900 of classes so far. 1,000 hours of
classes so far.
And uh you should come, okay? It's
really frustrating for me when people
don't come.
And uh I've made a commitment to finish
it. We're about halfway through, I
think. And I'm throwing Tsongkhapa's
Lamrim Chenmo emptiness
teaching, which is
dessert.
So, it's going to take another 7 or 8
years, I think. We've been at it for
about 8 years, I think. And uh
you should come. It really frustrates
me. I often get people
asking me for advice that I covered the
last Lamrim retreat for 10 days, and and
it's just, you know,
then I have to do this irritation
meditation. And
Okay, so
Okay, it's, you know, it's cool. It's
really, really nice, okay? Now, second
thing,
uh we're going to start ACI
teacher training. So, at this college
it has kind of demonstrated to me
I'm not a very good teacher trainer. I I
I'm a I enjoy teaching
uh ideas. I love ideas, and I enjoy
teaching Buddhism. It's my favorite
thing. I told V, the attention I get is
unmatchable.
But uh
but the I'm not a very good teacher
teacher. I just kind of say, "Well, here
I taught you, so go do it, you know?"
And so
we've had the college here for 2 years
now.
We're teaching DCI teachers. It's a
formal
program. It has four parts. We call it
the four legs of the table.
Uh first part is content. So, our
content is uh
unmatchable in the world by about a
thousand degrees. Like, I'm not worried
about the content. The content is
extraordinary, and even I admit it. Uh
but it's not my content. It's Buddhism.
It's like, "Dude, I'm a mission, dude."
So, um which I'm not. So,
you know, the content is is cool. Second
is
how to teach, you know, which I have
never taught. I just always thought if I
just taught people would watch me and
they could teach.
Uh
and I have a natural ability to teach
and and it it took me many years to
realize not everybody does. Like if
you're a natural athlete, if you're a
good runner, she used to outrun all the
boys,
then you don't think about it, you see?
So, uh
I don't think about teaching. I just do
it, you know, but it's but I
But but but the teacher training for
DCI, which happens in this room mostly,
and Lucia's been there, a lot of people
have been there, it's uh
teach you how to teach, teach you how to
present to an audience.
And I've watched the people for 2 years.
And that's mainly Orリード, who has a
education degree in education.
So, uh she knows how to teach teaching
and she has all these tricks that she
learned in college and she uses them and
people who were not good teachers,
people who were shy, people who st-
stuttered a lot,
people who were, you know, couldn't just
lost it in front of an audience, uh
they've gotten really good.
And it's amazing. They use a lot of
videos, stuff. People video each other
on their phones and then they all
critique the videos and it's cool.
So, uh
we're going to steal everything
for the ACI teacher training. Okay, so
that's the second thing.
Uh third thing is uh
What is the third thing? Uh
Production, I'd say. You can say either
order.
I Yeah, production, like
a lot of people are really good teachers
and they don't know how to get people to
come to their talk.
They don't know anything about What's
that th-
Facebook is it called?
Uh what's that newer one? Instagram.
Instagram.
I was in Germany. They introduced people
by the number of downloads they have.
Oh, this is Tobias Matthew.
Uh he's What's his last name? Beyspeck.
Beyspeck?
Tobias Beck. This is Tobias Beck, 12
million.
And this is what's her name, 20 million.
And I'm like
What's a 12 million? And this is how
many downloads they have from their
podcast, you know?
So, they introduced people with the
number of
downloads. I don't even know how to do a
download.
And uh
so
I was in Japan. We kicked out
We kicked out the old organizer.
Uh he was marketing and he we said, "Did
you market this event? Like you were
there." We sang uh
that hippie song.
What was that?
Yeah.
And uh 40 people came and uh so I said,
"Did you advertise this event?" He said,
"Yeah."
I said, "What did you do?" He said, he
took me to the 7-Eleven and he showed me
the poster he put up.
And I'm like, "Okay.
We got to work on this. Okay, so uh
So, yeah, how to market your event, how
to Rinpoche had a very My teacher had a
very beautiful philosophy. He said,
"Look,
I'm not trying to toot my own horn.
That's a bad karma, you know? I'm not
trying to
to become the person with the most
downloads in the world. It's not my
thing.
But if you guys, my students, uh and he
was saying it to me,
if there's a person in the world who
wanted to come and didn't hear about it,
you failed as my disciple, you know? And
then that was a heavy
thing, you know? And uh so really
it's how do you get the word out that
you're having a class to the people who
want to come
and you don't fail people that way,
okay?
Uh and it's not like going door-to-door
and trying to convince people to come to
your class, okay? Although, if you want
to do that, I don't know.
Okay, and then the last one is
professional behavior. It boils down,
let's face it, it boils down to two
things, taking care of the money
carefully and not doing sex stuff with
other people's partners and stuff like
that. So, it but it just boils down, I
mean, after 66 years of my life,
this is professional behavior. Number
one, keep good track of your finances.
Be honest.
Be totally, totally, uh transparent, you
know? And then secondly, don't bother
other people uh in this way, okay? And
and be clean this way. So, that's
I just give the same lecture, it's
called the birds and the bees lecture
over and over again. And uh then there's
the money lecture. So, anyway, these
four
parts we're going to have in the teacher
training. The first teacher training
will be part of the Lamrim, April 12th
to 21st.
And we'll be going through ACI course
one. We'll be teaching you how to teach
ACI course one. Anyone's welcome to
apply, okay? Talk to Tim.
Uh at the same moment, I don't want to
freak out
ACI teachers who've been teaching for 30
years or 25 years, you know? So, in the
same breath,
I have to say,
uh we will uh
recognize people who have been teaching
ACI. We're not going to make you jump
through all the hoops again. And we have
a system that we're almost finished.
And it will take into account what
you've done before. And and but we will
still ask you
to do some basic training
on the parts of the table that we didn't
talk about in the past, okay? Just to
help you and to help us. So, don't freak
out. I'm not trying to kick anybody out
of being an ACI teacher. The goal is
still to have as many ACI teachers as
there are people in the world.
And uh
So So just feel comfortable. And
And I after long talks with Hector, for
example,
uh
we can't expect everyone in the world
like like ACI is strong in Israel, for
example, or ACI is strong in Argentina,
not bad.
Uh we can't expect everyone to fly 12
hours here 15 hours
every time we do a teacher training. So
we're going to do a mix of online and
offline, okay? When I took my gemology
degree,
which I have, too,
uh
the one I took from the Great Britain
Gemological Society, extremely difficult
to pass. And uh the American one, which
is always less difficult.
And uh
you did part
online, which at the time was called
letters in the mail.
And you did part
uh you did part of it in the lab. So you
had to
uh go through You know, you submitted a
lot of homeworks on
uh by mail at the time. Now it would be
online.
And then uh
you every quarter or something you had
to fly to New York and uh
pass a difficult lab test. And And it
was tough.
I remember it was 20 stones.
And you had to get it perfect. And if
you failed one stone,
identifying one stone, uh you you had to
take it over. And it was expensive,
okay? So I don't know
how we're going to pay for this, I don't
know. Tim's going to figure it out. Uh
We didn't talk about it.
That's all.
Um
But we asked the existing teachers to I
don't know
to cooperate, you know? Like don't be
stubborn about it, you know? We're
trying to
do something which is uh protects
everybody
and uh makes it safe for everybody and
we want our students to be safe and we
want
teachers to be good and we want to have
some kind of way to check your
performance.
Uh my mom was a school teacher.
I remember the day she would come home.
These mom and met my mom because they
were both teaching in the same school.
That's how we met each other.
And my mom used to come home really
pissed off twice a year and she'd say,
"I had the the teacher checker person
was in my class today." You know what
I'm saying? I'd say, "Don't worry, Mom.
It's okay." She'd say, "Ah, they don't
know anything."
You know, and
that's going to happen with ACI. Okay.
Uh
but just relax and it's okay and
you know, the goal is more teachers
and and then don't hurt anybody. Okay?
That's all. Those two things. Okay?
That's all.
Uh and don't get scandals and don't get
in the press and stuff like that. Okay.
All right, here we go.
Uh
I thought it'd be a good time to do
questions and then maybe I'll go back
and do a a final verse.
Uh but I propose we do questions about
any subject you want. Okay? It doesn't
have to be
relevant. All right? You can talk about
anything you're curious about. We have
in this room
these intense Dharma veterans and uh
it's really it's kind of fun for me.
It's been a pleasant weekend for me to
to be in a room.
I guess there's a couple hundred years
of practice in this room right now. Uh
seriously.
More than that.
Maybe we got a thousand years in this
room.
Uh but it's pretty amazing but it's I
think your questions might be
interesting. So,
go for it.
Uh
Peter's going to choose the people so I
don't get in trouble.
So, guess
Mike's not working.
Is it on?
Thank you, Geshe-la.
Um so, in in my in the text that I'm
working on with you, um there is um in
the discussion of the independent group
in the middle way school, there's the
presentation of the metaphor of the
magician.
And in that um metaphor, they they
relate the basic three characters to who
they are in real life. And so, we know
that the people standing around and
being affected by the
the spell in the
uh the
the powder are social cables, are
people who've not seen emptiness
directly. And we know that the magician
who has
thrown the powder and knows what he has
done,
um
he has the experience of of having his
eyes fooled, but his mind is not fooled.
Mhm. He knows what's happened. Now, the
the third person I've heard described as
as an Arya in the direct perception of
emptiness. But now, given what has been
talked about today, I'm not entirely
sure of how we would what what we would
call that person. Would he he have to be
a Buddha then?
Uh why so?
Um because um what you said until you're
a 10th level bodhisattva
All right. there's still the shadow of
the karma of Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, good. I My understanding and and I
think you might find it explained
different ways by different people, but
my understanding is that the person who
walks up later,
so, this and and
didn't get a mantra,
which is the ancient meaning of mantra,
uh a magic spell,
and who didn't get magic powder thrown
on them and doesn't see a horse where
there's only a stick
that this person is like the Arya in the
direct perception of emptiness. Yeah.
And what you're saying is that
you know, they have a feeling about the
stick.
But they have deep seeds for the seeing
the horse or something like that. That's
true. I guess you could say that. I
don't think they have to be a Buddha in
this
image. Yeah, in this particular image.
Uh what but I'll say something
interesting
that he's going to cover later on
because he's going to pick on that
school.
And he's going to say
he's going to challenge us
to think about is there
trying to draw distinction
between existing from its own side,
existing by definition, existing through
some nature of its own, you know,
existing in and of itself.
The the lower middle way school tries to
draw distinction between this.
And then he challenges it and he's and
he he says, "Really, you guys are the
same as the other schools.
As long as you keep trying to make a
distinction
between different kinds of
self-existence,
then you you don't understand any of
them."
It's just
Yeah, which is kind of
radical thing to say, okay?
Any other questions?
Scratch here.
That's my answer.
During the presentation of the of the
pen
uh we come up to the point of the
luminous image and there's sometimes you
take a
you go deeper at that moment and you say
if you want to know the luminous image
is
it's um
you can think of it as
uh what you say in Dharmakirti school
it's defined as when your mind removes
everything that the pen, for example, is
not then the I the luminous image of a
pen pops up in your mind.
Uh and then that's how we explain those
frames opening is how we see things and
hear things, etc.
But I was exam And then the final thing
is that that luminous image, according
to Dharmakirti school, I believe, is
unchanging. It is in their school. Yeah.
So then I thought about um
what a
I had a question about what a wonderful
thing it is to try to imagine
uh a smallest frame of sound which would
never change.
Well, how how strange that would be. So
I had a question about that. An
archetype of sound? Yes, exactly.
Wow.
I didn't think about it. Uh
the Abhidharma school, which we studied
in the
I think it came up last time we were
together.
What did they say about sound? Quality
of space. Oh, it's so ephemeral. It's a
quality of space. It's something about
how ephemeral it is. Yeah, it doesn't
count as giggy dupa? Yeah, it doesn't
count as substance because it's so
ephemeral. It Yeah, like the Abhidharma
school tries to say, and it's not
correct, that it's different from
visible form. That what you hear is
different, and it can't be contained I
think it was that it can't be contained
within a human
mind stream
because it's gone by the time you hear
it. Something like that.
But uh I don't know. I I can't even
imagine an archetype of a sound, I
guess.
I guess it'd be a nice meditation to do,
to try to do
to try to think of an archetype of
sound. Uh
And I I guess it's it wouldn't be so
weird. It'd be the opposite of all that
it's not or something like that. Yeah.
My own experience is that the first time
it was visible,
it was a visible object. It wasn't a
auditory
object. So I think uh
the Abhidharma also says that uh
somewhere it says 90% of human
experiences is visible.
And uh the other senses account for very
little.
Uh like most people relate to what they
see.
And they're living in the world of what
they see. So, I I'm I think I can say,
although I haven't
asked everyone who ever had the
experience, uh
that your first experience about
catching
the image coming out of a karmic seed,
which is the highest
part of the second time, uh is probably
will always with a visible object,
unless you're blind already or
something.
I'm I'm guessing. Yeah.
That doesn't help much, I know.
That's all I can think about it.
Okay, other questions?
Um
First, I have a question for everybody
else. If anyone's going down to Phoenix
tomorrow, if they could let me know,
that'd be great.
Um Anybody going down to Phoenix
tomorrow?
If we could talk after, that'd be
awesome. Uh Geshe-la, do physical things
only cause physical things?
Yeah, okay, that's a good question.
Uh
My answer is going to come from a Yeah,
take the mic away.
Consider physical things. Yeah, uh yeah.
This question is traditionally comes up
in the examination of the relationship
between mind and body.
And uh so,
is it
is it is it that uh the mind cannot be
affected by physical things? And uh
because most people, okay, human nature
is to equate the mind with a physical
part of the body like the brain.
And uh that's mistaken.
Uh awareness is
cannot be weighed, cannot be cut, cannot
be
measured in that way. But there's a
famous discussion about the connection
between mind and body.
There's a sutra discussion and as you
know there's a tantra discussion. So the
sutra discussion says uh
and you've heard me say it many times,
when you get nervous at work you get a
ulcer.
So the mind must be able to affect the
body. And uh
when you drink alcohol your mind gets
more stupid. And uh
so there must be a connection between
the physical things and and the mind. On
a tantric level you know it's lung sem
tzu pi ti po which is uh prana
and the thoughts move together.
Which is an interesting in the
discussion when you teach the
the four What do you say?
Yeah, when you teach the fourth parts of
a karma.
She sam pa jo wo tar tuk, right? The
four steps to
creating a karmic seed.
Uh the final one which is the coffee
meditation which is to enjoy
the good things you've been doing today
at the end of the day.
It's interesting when you teach it to
teach it in terms of of the tantric
presentation of the relationship between
the physical and the mental because uh
you can talk about prana
uh
traveling on thought
and vice versa, uh linked and and how it
kind of psychically heats up the
karmic seed. Uh it speeds it speeds its
growth. If you think about a good karma
you did
the prana moves with the thought and and
literally heats up the seed somehow. How
much should I And that's a nice
thing to talk about I think. Give I'm in
it more. So that's my answer but go
ahead. Like in the sense of
Like can a physical thing create a
changing thing that's not physical
or mental? Like doesn't action create a
seed and isn't an action a physical
thing?
So how are we doing an action that's
creating
a seed? A How are we doing something
physical that's creating something
that's not the changing thing that's not
physical or mental?
Yeah, I understand. Hmm, that's an
interesting question.
Uh semba yiki leno, right?
Uh
de che lu dang ngakile. Uh
thinking is karma
of the thought and then what you
what it triggers is physical and verbal
karma. So maybe it's all tied up with
the mental side of a physical karma.
No, according to Tsongkhapa's
little poem which uh you know,
Sho Pings struggling through for the
next five years.
It uh
the thought precedes the action. So
maybe it's the thought that that
is primary in planting the seed. How's
that?
Cuz the thought always precedes the
action.
Uh
Yeah, the physical uh giving is
secondary to the intention to give which
is my intention is 90% traditionally of
a karma. How's that?
Same problem though because it's the
mental movement of the mind that's
creating something which is changing but
neither physical nor mental,
right?
Uh yeah. Well, if a mental thing could
create a physical thing, I don't think a
changing thing is neither physical nor
mental such a big jump.
Mhm.
An act of
body language
isn't really isn't the main thing
creating the seed.
Exactly. In that case,
uh which is the famous point that that
intention is primary.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I understand. I think you can cross
those lines. I mean, if you want you
want me to really answer the question.
Uh I think uh
I think we can say
that uh a mental activity can cross the
line and create a thing which is neither
mental nor physical, but which is
changing. I I would say yes. I would say
duh.
And then I'd let you fight with me.
Okay. Next, one more.
Don't ask him. He's too expensive.
Uh so about uh ACI fives. Um
So Wait, never do that cuz I always
forget what you're saying.
Okay. It's a It's about karma, about uh
Okay, okay, okay, okay. It's a Chandra
It's a Chandra Kirti question. So
uh Annie has an amazing um
highly developed nose and olfactory
olfactory and taste. Super J had that.
Yeah, so she can smell anything, which
is, you know, and and taste. So at the
hotel room, she tastes the water and it
tastes bad to her, but it tastes fine to
me.
So two different karmas there, right? So
Chandra Kirti says that we the um if you
take the
uh
if you take the hungry ghost and the
human and the god,
they're seeing three different things,
wet and flowing, right? And and Chandra
Kirti says they're seeing those three
things based on their species,
in a sense. That if it's human, Mhm. we
see water. As a hungry ghost, we're
going to see pus and blood. As a god,
we're going to see nectar.
So it seems, and this is really a
question of cultural relativism, too. It
seems like there's some things which are
species-based
and some things which are um adjustable.
Mhm. And I'm wondering what that
delineation is between those two.
Yeah, you know, when I teach,
rebirth in DCI,
which is illegal.
So,
you see what I mean? Uh, we try to avoid
the question of rebirth in DCI. Uh,
when we get to the fourth way that karma
opens,
we have to dance around it a little bit,
which is, uh,
how seeds tend to multiply until you
have more seeds at the end of your life
than you could possibly use up at the
end of your life, but
justice demands that they don't get
canceled.
And we leave it kind of there. It's kind
of cute.
We kind of leave it there, and all these
smart business people, they're like, you
can see they're going click, click,
click, click, click, and they they
figured out, and we don't say anything.
But we say you reach the end of your If
karma doubles, if a karma done on August
1st is a million times stronger August
31st,
then you must end your life with more
seeds than you begin, and it's been
piling up, so
and seeds cannot be canceled. So, uh, it
must be that when you come to the end of
your life, you know, and that's the
fourth manner
in which karma is taught. That's the
fourth quality of karma. The way the
fourth flower,
the fourth way that karma opens is is in
the next life.
But we can't go there in DCI, so we kind
of leave it at We give them the two
parts of the equation, and then we just
kind of go on to the next subject, and
it's kind of fun cuz I like to take a
break at that point cuz they go out for
coffee, and you can see them
then you can kind of see them stop
drinking, and they hit it, you know, and
they're like,
"Oh, that means I must have a future
life." You see, but you don't say it.
You cannot allowed to say it in DCI.
Then, uh,
there's something I like to say that
that I say over and over
and I can see people don't get it.
But, I'll try it again, okay? Here we
go.
Which is the answer to the question.
There's a traditional sense, even among
people who accept rebirth,
that
there must be
some kind of bardo. And and the more you
study bardo,
the more often you see references that
bardo is the time it takes to get to
your new location.
Okay?
Uh it's more it's most often presented
that way. Who can tell me why word?
For for fit for
50, okay, I'll do 50. Because you're
moving
you're moving in space, so
Because a tree cannot come from a seed
without an intermediate
We talked about it upstairs.
Okay, I'll give you a clue and it
cancels the financial.
Uh
formless realm.
Because they don't have a body There's
no bardo for when you're headed for the
formless realm, cuz there's no place to
go. So, it doesn't take any time to get
there. So, you don't need a spirit being
after the dying before you get reborn to
travel to where you're going, even by
supernatural means,
cuz you just start living where you
died.
Um
But, if you go deeper, you know, and
then I like to go into this long story
of why
you know, when people hear the word
rebirth and the way Abhidharma explains
the word rebirth with all these spirit
beings after you die,
it starts to feel like By the way, uh
spirit being in the bardo, bardo being,
has karma to pass through any physical
object except
the cells of skin at the back of the
wound.
They They get stuck there. Okay, that's
the Abhidharma
presentation. Therefore, people start to
think that their soul
gets released when they die.
And then I like to call it the dog body
factory in Kansas. I'm sorry if anyone's
from Kansas.
But, you know, we kind of feel when your
mom talks about rebirth,
uh
that there's a place where they make dog
bodies. And then you have this image of
a butterfly net with a really long
stick. And their souls going east-west
across the United States. And then
somebody mean person at the dog factory
dog body factory
swings the net up and catches your soul.
And and opens up the back of the dog and
shoves your soul in there and shuts it
really fast.
And no, I mean
admit it. That's the picture you had
when you were a kid.
Something like that. Okay, not not you.
You're advanced. Okay. It was Canada. It
wasn't Albuquerque. Okay. Okay. So, it
was some kind of
Don't pick on Canada.
Uh it's the only moral country right
now. Um so, uh
that's the feeling we have. But,
uh when I I teach the emptiness of a
pen,
uh
yeah, thank you.
Uh at some point I like to do this. You
You guys probably saw me do it. And I
like to say this one's the same as this
one. Okay?
So,
why I see a pen is that every 65th of a
second
there's a image coming out of my mind.
There's a karmic seed opening and the
image is
is being laid on these parts. These two
parts. Okay? And
and that's how I'm seeing a pen. And
when I see a arm, it's the same. Right?
So, how long does it really take to
become a dog?
Yeah, it's 1/65
of a second forget bardo. I mean, if you
really understand emptiness,
there's no reason why it should take
There's also no logical reason why you'd
have to travel 1,000 miles.
Because this would become Kansas or this
would become Mars. It doesn't matter.
Your seed would open and it would become
a different location. So, um
Okay, this is where I lose people. You
ready? And if you look at this one
and you see a paw,
you is a dog. is a dog.
And then I lose everybody and
everybody's like
They're just like, "Okay,
you know."
It's not that you're born as a dog.
It's that you see a paw.
The The picture that comes out of seed
makes a paw.
And that makes you a dog. Then you is a
dog. You see? So, that's all. So, don't
think of species
as a
as a self-existent thing somehow. You
see what I mean?
You create the species.
The la- The next seed that opens after
you die creates the species.
How's that?
And I I think I would say there could be
species exceptions,
you know, like
Somebody made me a
John was trying to get me a drink these
rotten pond scum pond scum
expensive green stuff.
And I just can't stop
experiencing it. He's gone, right? I'm
so lucky.
Uh I can't stop experiencing it as pond
scum
and I can't drink it, you know.
But we're the same species. Yeah, yeah,
yeah,
okay.
Good, let's do one more.
Then I'll wrap up.
So, forgive me because you may have
answered this. Probably.
Back to the idea of physical and mental
things, at the highest level is there
there is no distinction, right? Yeah,
right. They're both
They're both pictures. Okay.
Yeah.
That leaves us time to answer one more.
Two more.
Hello. Hi. Um, yesterday you were
talking about that the mind is
defective. Yeah.
And I've been a little troubled in my
mind because of that.
That's natural. Yeah, but uh
I've been I've been troubled because I
don't think it is defective and I
I even went to the dictionary to see
what defective really meant, right?
And uh I was I was looking that
when someone is defective, it used to
work well at some point.
Okay.
Or there's a lot of other things that
work well except one. Yeah, okay, good.
Right? So, uh
I am thinking that maybe defective is
not the correct word for that. So, maybe
it it will be another
word that should be used for describing
the mind. And I was using a
a
Anatole's son
uh as an example, right? Like, he's not
able to speak well or walk well and that
doesn't mean that he is defective. It
means that he's learning how to do it
and eventually he will get there, right?
So, uh the question is
why defective is the word chosen to
describe the mind? Yeah, good good
question. You know, you could probably
describe it as a
as a
as a sprout that hasn't grown into a
tree yet, right?
That's I think what you're saying. It
It's going to be perfection.
And it's not the tree yet. It's just
this tall. And it's not a whole tree
yet.
So, why call it defective? It's just on
its way.
Uh,
to be It's a short tree.
Don't call it a defective tree.
And I kind of That's good. I like that.
I think you can say that. Uh, I use
defective
as an exaggeration. I'm trying to push
people
to
uh
Yeah, it is an exaggeration. So, I I use
the word to to shock people. And to try
to get them to
Yeah, and it's I
Yeah, and it's not uh meant in a
derogatory way or something like that.
It's It's meant to shock people. Yeah,
that's all.
Uh, sometimes I say defective from the
factory.
Uh,
which is uh
also useful when you're a teacher and
you want to shock people. You can say
defective from the factory. And then
people say, "Well, when did the factory
start?" And you say, "Defective from the
factory since forever."
And that's also depressing.
Um
but uh
I think that's a good way. And And there
are ways of presenting
uh the human mind as a
as on its way to perfection, you know,
perfection to come.
And that's a beautiful way to say it.
And that's fine. That would be fine. I
think if depends on your audience,
maybe. And uh
I think it would be cool to call it
perfection, coming perfection, or
something like that.
Like cutie.
Say again? Coming along perfection.
Yeah, yeah, on its way to perfection.
Yeah, halfway to perfection.
That's fine. Yeah, that's fine. That's
cool.
That's cool. Yeah, Janice had one.
Thank you, Kashi Michael.
You're welcome. Uh my question's about
chich had rock um quality and
characteristic.
Um so when I think of my car, Toyota,
the characteristic, it has the quality
of being a car.
So if I think of the emptiness of it
doesn't have any self nature of itself
of being a car, could I say that the
emptiness of all cars in the parking lot
relate to
the overall quality of emptiness and
somehow link it that way? Yeah, you can.
I but I don't
and it's kind of where we went with the
parts of emptiness. Mhm. Yeah.
I just I felt like a parrot saying that
because I don't understand it.
Uh
First of all, I I wouldn't go there
right away. I mean, I I would Yeah, I
wouldn't say it's necessary to
understand chich had rock. I mean, you
could go there, but it's a little
difficult. It's the last thing Chönyi
Lama talks about in his long list of
candidates for things that have parts.
Uh he talks about the the parts of
emptiness. It's a very difficult subject
and you can see emptiness directly
just by focusing on cars.
You know, and I think it might be easier
to stay there.
Uh yeah, so you know, how does car
uh relate
to
to a physical car outside, you know? And
and
the meditation to teach that meditation
is kind of boring cuz it takes about 10
seconds.
And you know, like close your eyes
and then I say car and then you see what
comes up in your mind. And then I say,
"Okay."
Then I I always have a student drive a
car
right to this door and open the door and
say, you know, look at the car.
And then people look at the car, you
know, and uh
in the end
in the meditation
you want people to focus on what's the
difference.
You know, and so there's three levels
when you teach it, okay? One,
think about I'm going to say a word,
tell me what you see in your mind. And
then people close their eyes. This is
DCI level seven, right?
And people close their eyes and then you
wait a while and then you say car. And
then they're like, what the
You know, and then you repeat it. You
repeat it two, three times cuz they're
going to think you forgot the rest.
And you just say car. And then you say,
okay, observe what comes up in your
mind, okay?
And then you say
something like your car.
And then uh
or classically you can say a car, you
know.
A car, a particular car. And then they
think of their red RAV4, you know. They
have a picture in their mind of a
specific car, you know.
And then you take them to the window and
you show them a car. And then
then you play with what's the difference
between those three, okay? And uh
the punchline is that they're the same.
Okay, and but but invariably
people will say
the image that came up in their mind
when you said car
was fuzzier
than the image that came up in their
mind when you said a particular car.
And which is fuzzier than the
car you see when you open your eyes.
Okay, so that's a little tricky. Those
are three degrees of karma.
Those are just three degrees of karma,
okay? They're not a difference in the
object.
Okay, you have the karma to see one less
clearly than the other, but they're the
same object, okay? It's kind of weird.
So play with that. If you you can take
it to emptiness,
but I think you might get lost, you
know. It's pretty complex. Then it
becomes really complex. But if you want
to try, why not?
Okay, it's it's cuz you can't do the
karma one, so every day it just gets
kind of
like you're like, "Okay, what's next?"
You know. That's the nice thing about
the lion's stance. I think Maitreya
made it complex just to keep people
interested.
You know.
Cool. Okay, I'll wrap up. You ready? I'm
going to wrap up. All right. And uh
We didn't pick a date. Do you have a
date proposal?
Uh
I I was supposed to do it with V last
night, but we got interested in some
tacos.
Uh uh
July? Is July weird?
Well, I'm sorry. I can't control the
weather, I mean.
Oh.
How about beginning
I'm
Oh.
How about we negotiate it later with my
boss? Cuz that's her time.
No pressure.
Okay. We'll we'll go We'll talk about it
later. I'll I'll I'll try to do this
three times a year, four times a year.
Okay. And it's pleasant for me, too. I
get to hang out with my old friends and
compare how much hair we have left.
Okay. Peter's like,
Okay.
Uh
last word from the text.
Verse 150, okay? And he he just repeats
that it's easier not to think about this
stuff.
And it's easier just to go on with your
normal life. And it's
It's a strain
to worry about whether Rick's coming
from himself or not. You know, it's a
mental strain and we tend to avoid
that's why we avoid physical exercise. I
mean, it's it's easier not to, right?
And so there's a
on a on a beginning level
the only thing that can hurt the devil
in your mind
is logic. Think I like to call it clear
thinking others. I think it's more
acceptable to people if you call it
clear thinking instead of logic, right?
Logic is a bad word. So clear thinking.
Clear thinking
and
what do you call it? Persistent
clear thinking
is the only thing that can hurt the
devil
and it's a strain for a human being.
It's it's not convenient for us. It it
it's it's a strain and we don't do
things that are strain. We don't strain
ourselves
unless we have to, okay? So it takes a
kind of a courage
to strain yourself, okay?
And I would just say
accept that as part of a Buddhist life,
okay?
You're Buddhist. It's weird to talk to
Buddhist actually.
And uh
you're Buddhist
and uh
there's ideas you're supposed to try to
understand
and it's a strain.
And the devil is saying at 150
it's easier not to think about them and
it's easier just to do your normal
everyday life thing.
But then you die, then you run out of
time, okay? And I guess that you know,
those of us who are
over 35 now
what we can report
right? Is that time accelerates. Am I
right?
The older you get and
you don't want to get caught with your
karmic pants down.
You know,
so
you know,
do this drainful thinking now
and then you can relax later and don't
put it off cuz it's human nature to put
it off. Okay, so struggle with these
ideas. Read the
poem.
And if you read it lightly, don't
meditate on it, don't study it formally,
you know, go outside, sit on the porch,
take the paper with you, read one verse
and cogitate on it.
Does that count as meditation? I don't
know.
Just think about it, you know, and I I
predict that it will reveal new levels
to you. Okay, cuz he was extremely
profound writer and uh
I translated his tantric poetry
uh which was found in a monastery after
he died and uh
it's amazing and I gave it to a few
friends of mine and somebody published
it illegally.
Uh if you can find it, it's really cool.
Uh what's it called?
Uh Meditations from a tantric oven or
something like that.
Anyway, it's totally illegal. I think
it's you can get it almost anywhere.
And uh
you know, what you'll see from those
poems
uh is that you could sit on the porch
with them.
You know, every couple days take it out
with you on the porch and just sit there
and when the sun's going down or
something and then you know, it's a nice
time to be outside and
and enjoy yourself, you know, and have a
have something nice to drink and
and just sit there and and look at the
sunlight and and uh
see if you can find another level of
of wisdom below each verse. I predict
it's there. I say you will find
many levels. Okay, so let it be you kind
of your friend. And we can do this kind
of thing three, four times a year, okay?
And we'll come back to it. And then
maybe
you share what you saw
on the porch. Uh you know, you saw
levels of the
poetry that that I didn't see. And it'd
be nice to share with each other. I do
feel with this group
that it's what Rinpoche predicted of uh
when they all become Buddhas, they just
sit around and
teach each other in unison.
And what they say they knew they were
going to say.
Everyone knew you were going to say what
you say anyway, but people just enjoy
together. So, I kind of feel like this
particular group
it's kind of sweet
that we're all kind of like banged up
Dharma veterans.
We have chips and scratches and uh
and we enjoy each other at this time in
our life and and we talk about these
deep things and I try to see if there's
something you don't remember
or or vice versa, okay? So, look at the
poem
uh between. I I say you will find deep
things there. And uh cogitate on it.
When you tell people to meditate, it
feels like an obligation.
So, just cogitate
on it. And and you will you will see
sweet things, okay? Now,
by the way,
he mentions uh in verse 150 a thing
called the seven-part
analysis. And uh
it's extremely difficult.
And and I think it'd be sweet to pick it
up next time. Okay? So, I promise you in
this life or the next, depending on our
individual circumstances,
uh the seven the seven-part analysis.
Okay? Cool?
And that's where we'll pick up next
time, okay? All right. Thank you. Okay.
Tim? Oh.
Uh okay, it'd be fun to do in
By the way, we're going to have a
meeting upstairs about a project that
I'm very proud of that the Mexicans are
doing.
Uh, Mexico team
uh to help uh
23 million children
learn these principles in Mexico. So, I
think it's kind of
it's kind of cool. Hector, you having
He has a nice Australian
accent. Okay.
Okay. Thank you for coming.